<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Taryn Pratt</title>
    <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Taryn Pratt</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 06:00:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://tarynpivots.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating a 40TB SQL Server Database</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/migrating-40tb-sql-server-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/migrating-40tb-sql-server-database/</guid>
      <description>Initially, I wasn’t sure whether to write about this migration project, but when I randomly asked if people would be interested, the response was overwhelming. This was a long, kind of boring, very repetitive, and at times incredibly frustrating project, but I learned a lot, and maybe someone else will learn from this too. There may be far better ways to move this amount of data. In the path I went down, there was a huge amount of juggling that had to take place (I’ll explain that later).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2019 Tuple Mover Behavior Change</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/sql-server-2019-tuple-mover-behavior-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/sql-server-2019-tuple-mover-behavior-change/</guid>
      <description>This is a follow-up to my post about an issue with clustered columnstore, when upgrading from SQL Server 2017 to SQL Server 2019. After extensive testing and working with support, I wanted to share some information about a change in SQL Server 2019 that might impact others.
Overview I suggest reading my other post first, it&amp;rsquo;ll only take a few minutes. I&amp;rsquo;ll wait&amp;hellip;
However, if you really don&amp;rsquo;t want to read it, here&amp;rsquo;s a quick recap on the initial issue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2019 Aggressive Clustered Columnstore Cleanup</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/aggressive-clustered-columnstore-cleanup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/aggressive-clustered-columnstore-cleanup/</guid>
      <description>In late March 2020, we upgraded our production SQL Servers to SQL Server 2019 with CU3. After finishing the upgrade, we hit an issue with clustered columnstore that we hadn&amp;rsquo;t experienced in the previous version of SQL, SQL Server 2017. The issue also wasn&amp;rsquo;t something we encountered during our extensive testing on various servers in development, which dated back to September 2019. The problem has been mitigated, but I wanted to share our experience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A gotcha when upgrading to SQL Server 2019</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/system-view-gotcha-with-sql-server-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/system-view-gotcha-with-sql-server-2019/</guid>
      <description>In my last post, I mentioned that I started the process of upgrading Stack Overflow to SQL Server 2019. This week I tackled our first production servers and after upgrading, we hit a small issue aka a gotcha because we were using an old system view. Below is a recap of what I encountered.
A Little Background The servers I upgraded were the three SQL Servers that run Stack Overflow for Teams.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recovering Lost Linked Servers</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/recovering-lost-linked-servers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/recovering-lost-linked-servers/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I kicked off a project to start moving us to SQL Server 2019. During my initial review of our servers, I found quite a few (9 total) that were still running on Windows Server 2012 R2. This meant that I would need to upgrade the operating system and move us to SQL Server 2019. Having completed plenty of SQL Server upgrades, as well as operating system upgrades, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t possibly make a mistake, right?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Perils of Querying SQL Server Replicas Under Load</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/perils-querying-sql-replica-under-load/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/perils-querying-sql-replica-under-load/</guid>
      <description>Last week at Stack Overflow we had an internal hack-a-thon, or as we call it, a make-a-thon. I was on the bug-bashing team, which is the team that attempts to fix smallish bugs we haven’t gotten around to fixing, due to other time-constraints. I was tagged to investigate a bug about duplicate badges being awarded because it looked to possibly be an easy fix in SQL. At first glance it looked simple enough, but once I started digging in, I figured out very quickly it wouldn’t be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>T-SQL Tuesday #122 - Impostor Syndrome</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/t-sql-tuesday-122-impostor-syndrome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/t-sql-tuesday-122-impostor-syndrome/</guid>
      <description>This month&amp;rsquo;s T-SQL Tuesday is hosted by Jon Shaulis, who has asked that we talk about impostor syndrome. This subject is close to my heart, as I have dealt with it throughout my career.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t study computer science or engineering in college. I never even took a computer class. I sort of just fell into working as a web developer because I had someone tell me they wouldn’t hire me due to lack of experience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hitting Parallel_Redo_Flow_Control waits with Availability Groups</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/parallel-redo-flow-control-waits-and-availability-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/parallel-redo-flow-control-waits-and-availability-groups/</guid>
      <description>In late June 2019, June 26th to be exact, we experienced an outage on Stack Overflow for about 11 minutes. It&amp;rsquo;s not unusual that we had an outage. They happen. Not often, but they do still happen. This one, however, was a little different because it was caused by a maintenance job that was running on our primary SQL Server for Stack Overflow.
The job that caused it was something I&amp;rsquo;d noticed about a month prior, but had stopped it before an actual outage occurred.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally, My first PASS Summit</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/my-first-pass-summit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/my-first-pass-summit/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with SQL Server for a long time, and have always wanted to attend PASS. For one reason of another, with numerous employers, I hadn’t been able to go. The answer was always no. &amp;lt;insert sad face&amp;gt;
The biggest blocker was always the cost.
The conference is expensive.
Seattle is expensive.
It has always been impossible to get my employer to foot the bill for it.
This year I was incredibly lucky that my employer, Stack Overflow, paid for my trip to PASS Summit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Stack Overflow upgraded from Windows Server 2012</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-stack-overflow-upgraded-from-windows-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-stack-overflow-upgraded-from-windows-2012/</guid>
      <description>Warning: This post is long. While working through this massive server upgrade/migration process, tears were shed, many cuss words were said, along with a general feeling of frustration, which ultimately culminated into extreme happiness once the migration was completed. The scale and complexity of the implementation factor into the length of this post, and I’ll share my thought process on how this was executed, so here goes.
Last year, when we upgraded to SQL Server 2017 we didn&amp;rsquo;t make any changes to the operating system on our main production servers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How we upgraded Stack Overflow to SQL Server 2017</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-we-upgraded-stackoverflow-to-sql-server-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 19:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-we-upgraded-stackoverflow-to-sql-server-2017/</guid>
      <description>This post has been rattling around in my head for months, and with SQL Server 2019 on the horizon, I figured I&amp;rsquo;d finally put my thoughts down, especially since I know we might hit some of the same issues when we upgrade.
A quick background, when I became the DBA at Stack Overflow, we had various versions of SQL Server in place &amp;mdash; the majority were at some level of SQL Server 2016, each with a different CU or SP installed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pivoting yet again - New blog and domain</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/pivoting-yet-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/pivoting-yet-again/</guid>
      <description>Almost a year ago, in November 2017, I moved back into a more technical role at Stack Overflow and became a Database Administrator. During this time, I have wanted to relaunch my blog, as it&amp;rsquo;s been over three years since I really wrote anything (yes, I&amp;rsquo;m terrible).
Well, that time has finally come.
After spending a few weeks, looking at various options to replace Wordpress, I finally decided on using Hugo and Netlify.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ch Ch Ch Changes are afoot</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/ch-ch-ch-changes-are-afoot/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2015 22:49:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/ch-ch-ch-changes-are-afoot/</guid>
      <description>Well it&amp;rsquo;s been an interesting couple months and there are quite a few changes going on in my life, but before I get into what&amp;rsquo;s coming up, I feel that I need to give a bit of an overview of my journey thus far.
I never thought about becoming a developer. When I was growing up, I loved school (yeah, I&amp;rsquo;m weird), I loved math and science (even weirder), I was going to be a doctor, work on genetics, or something similar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using powershell to fix server space issues</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/using-powershell-to-fix-server-space-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 18:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/using-powershell-to-fix-server-space-issues/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, we were running into severe disk space and memory issues on our development servers at work. Our set-up is a bit odd, we have 3 servers - one for the transactions, one for the web interface, and the final one for reporting. Using transactional replication we have databases that can exist on all 3 servers. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s can be a real nightmare to maintain, but anyone who works with replication already knows this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Saturday Adventures</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/sql-saturday-adventures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 16:50:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/sql-saturday-adventures/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks bit over a month ago, I took the plunge and attended my very first SQL Saturday, SQL Saturday #370 in Phoenix. I&amp;rsquo;ve never had a chance to go to any of the local user group events or another SQL Saturday due to scheduling issues, etc. but this year I reshuffled things so I could take part. I&amp;rsquo;m really glad that I did, I truly learned a lot of stuff and I also realized I know more than I probably give myself credit for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to rotate rows into columns in MySQL</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-to-rotate-rows-into-columns-in-mysql/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2015 19:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-to-rotate-rows-into-columns-in-mysql/</guid>
      <description>I have answered a lot of MySQL pivot questions over on Stack Overflow and a few over on Database Administrators and have learned some things about how to transform data in MySQL.
Unfortunately, MySQL does not have PIVOT function, so in order to rotate data from rows into columns you will have to use a CASE expression along with an aggregate function.
Let&amp;rsquo;s set up some sample data.
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 44 45 46  create table products ( prod_id int not null, prod_name varchar(50) not null, primary key (prod_id) ); insert into products (prod_id, prod\name) values (1, &amp;#39;Shoes&amp;#39;), (2, &amp;#39;Pants&amp;#39;), (3, &amp;#39;Shirt&amp;#39;); create table reps ( rep_id int not null, rep_name varchar(50) not null, primary key (rep_id) ); insert into reps (rep_id, rep_name) values (1, &amp;#39;John&amp;#39;), (2, &amp;#39;Sally&amp;#39;), (3, &amp;#39;Joe&amp;#39;), (4, &amp;#39;Bob&amp;#39;); create table sales ( prod_id INT NOT NULL, rep_id INT NOT NULL, sale_date datetime not null, quantity int not null, PRIMARY KEY (prod_id, rep_id, sale_date), FOREIGN KEY (prod_id) REFERENCES products(prod_id), FOREIGN KEY (rep_id) REFERENCES reps(rep_id) ); insert into sales (prod_id, rep_id, sale_date, quantity) values (1, 1, &amp;#39;2013-05-16&amp;#39;, 20), (1, 1, &amp;#39;2013-06-19&amp;#39;, 2), (2, 1, &amp;#39;2013-07-03&amp;#39;, 5), (3, 1, &amp;#39;2013-08-22&amp;#39;, 27), (3, 2, &amp;#39;2013-06-27&amp;#39;, 500), (3, 2, &amp;#39;2013-01-07&amp;#39;, 150), (1, 2, &amp;#39;2013-05-01&amp;#39;, 89), (2, 2, &amp;#39;2013-02-14&amp;#39;, 23), (1, 3, &amp;#39;2013-01-29&amp;#39;, 19), (3, 3, &amp;#39;2013-03-06&amp;#39;, 13), (2, 3, &amp;#39;2013-04-18&amp;#39;, 1), (2, 3, &amp;#39;2013-08-03&amp;#39;, 78), (2, 3, &amp;#39;2013-07-22&amp;#39;, 69);   We can easily query the rep, sales, and product data by joining the tables:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Did somebody say pivot?</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/did-somebody-say-pivot/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 00:56:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/did-somebody-say-pivot/</guid>
      <description>Paging bluefeet, there is a PIVOT question to be answered.
While that might seem like a joke, it has really happened, especially over on Stack Overflow. If you have seen any of my posts, then the chances are that I was answering a PIVOT question (or something similar). At this time of this post almost 20% of my total answers (over 3k) have been on pivot questions.
You might ask yourself, why pivot?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Late to the party</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/late-to-the-party/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 02:00:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/late-to-the-party/</guid>
      <description>Boy, I am sure behind the times with having a tech type of blog, but being late is better than never. I am going to try to use this platform to discuss some of my tech journeys while I delve into my new job as a DBA developer. I have worked on SQL Server in the past, but I will be venturing into Oracle development as well as more in depth SQL Server stuff.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 01:36:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/about/</guid>
      <description>Just a little blurb&amp;hellip;I&amp;rsquo;m a former web and application developer, and Community Manager who is currently working as a Database Administrator at Stack Overflow. When I&amp;rsquo;m not at my desk, I&amp;rsquo;m probably running or pretending to be a woodworker. I can be reached via email at taryn.e.pratt (SHIFT+2) gmail (period) com*.
* If you are human, you should be able to decipher the email address.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>