<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Windows Server 2016 on Taryn Pratt - Pivots and other SQL fun</title>
    <link>https://tarynpivots.com/tags/windows-server-2016/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Windows Server 2016 on Taryn Pratt - Pivots and other SQL fun</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 06:00:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://tarynpivots.com/tags/windows-server-2016/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Recovering Lost Linked Servers</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/recovering-lost-linked-servers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/recovering-lost-linked-servers/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I kicked off a project to start moving us to SQL Server 2019. During my initial review of our servers, I found quite a few (9 total) that were still running on Windows Server 2012 R2. This meant that I would need to upgrade the operating system and move us to SQL Server 2019. Having completed plenty of SQL Server upgrades, as well as operating system upgrades, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t possibly make a mistake, right?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Stack Overflow upgraded from Windows Server 2012</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-stack-overflow-upgraded-from-windows-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-stack-overflow-upgraded-from-windows-2012/</guid>
      <description>Warning: This post is long. While working through this massive server upgrade/migration process, tears were shed, many cuss words were said, along with a general feeling of frustration, which ultimately culminated into extreme happiness once the migration was completed. The scale and complexity of the implementation factor into the length of this post, and I’ll share my thought process on how this was executed, so here goes.
Last year, when we upgraded to SQL Server 2017 we didn&amp;rsquo;t make any changes to the operating system on our main production servers.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>