<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sql Server on Taryn Pratt</title>
    <link>https://tarynpivots.com/tags/sql-server/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sql Server on Taryn Pratt</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 06:00:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://tarynpivots.com/tags/sql-server/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hitting Parallel_Redo_Flow_Control waits with Availability Groups</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/parallel-redo-flow-control-waits-and-availability-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/parallel-redo-flow-control-waits-and-availability-groups/</guid>
      <description>In late June 2019, June 26th to be exact, we experienced an outage on Stack Overflow for about 11 minutes. It&amp;rsquo;s not unusual that we had an outage. They happen. Not often, but they do still happen. This one, however, was a little different because it was caused by a maintenance job that was running on our primary SQL Server for Stack Overflow.
The job that caused it was something I&amp;rsquo;d noticed about a month prior, but had stopped it before an actual outage occurred.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally, My first PASS Summit</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/my-first-pass-summit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/my-first-pass-summit/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with SQL Server for a long time, and have always wanted to attend PASS. For one reason of another, with numerous employers, I hadn’t been able to go. The answer was always no. &amp;lt;insert sad face&amp;gt;
The biggest blocker was always the cost.
The conference is expensive.
Seattle is expensive.
It has always been impossible to get my employer to foot the bill for it.
This year I was incredibly lucky that my employer, Stack Overflow, paid for my trip to PASS Summit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Stack Overflow upgraded from Windows Server 2012</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-stack-overflow-upgraded-from-windows-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-stack-overflow-upgraded-from-windows-2012/</guid>
      <description>Warning: This post is long. While working through this massive server upgrade/migration process, tears were shed, many cuss words were said, along with a general feeling of frustration, which ultimately culminated into extreme happiness once the migration was completed. The scale and complexity of the implementation factor into the length of this post, and I’ll share my thought process on how this was executed, so here goes.
Last year, when we upgraded to SQL Server 2017 we didn&amp;rsquo;t make any changes to the operating system on our main production servers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How we upgraded Stack Overflow to SQL Server 2017</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-we-upgraded-stackoverflow-to-sql-server-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 19:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-we-upgraded-stackoverflow-to-sql-server-2017/</guid>
      <description>This post has been rattling around in my head for months, and with SQL Server 2019 on the horizon, I figured I&amp;rsquo;d finally put my thoughts down, especially since I know we might hit some of the same issues when we upgrade.
A quick background, when I became the DBA at Stack Overflow, we had various versions of SQL Server in place &amp;mdash; the majority were at some level of SQL Server 2016, each with a different CU or SP installed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using powershell to fix server space issues</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/using-powershell-to-fix-server-space-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 18:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/using-powershell-to-fix-server-space-issues/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, we were running into severe disk space and memory issues on our development servers at work. Our set-up is a bit odd, we have 3 servers - one for the transactions, one for the web interface, and the final one for reporting. Using transactional replication we have databases that can exist on all 3 servers. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s can be a real nightmare to maintain, but anyone who works with replication already knows this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Saturday Adventures</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/sql-saturday-adventures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 16:50:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/sql-saturday-adventures/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks bit over a month ago, I took the plunge and attended my very first SQL Saturday, SQL Saturday #370 in Phoenix. I&amp;rsquo;ve never had a chance to go to any of the local user group events or another SQL Saturday due to scheduling issues, etc. but this year I reshuffled things so I could take part. I&amp;rsquo;m really glad that I did, I truly learned a lot of stuff and I also realized I know more than I probably give myself credit for.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>