<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>powershell on Taryn Pratt - Pivots and other SQL fun</title>
    <link>https://tarynpivots.com/tags/powershell/</link>
    <description>Recent content in powershell on Taryn Pratt - Pivots and other SQL fun</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 04:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://tarynpivots.com/tags/powershell/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Deploying My SQL Server Maintenance Scripts</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/2020/deploying-my-sql-server-maintenance-scripts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/2020/deploying-my-sql-server-maintenance-scripts/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I listed out the tools I use with SQL Server. Some of the tools are SQL scripts that need to be deployed to each server. If you have 1-2 SQL Servers, manually deploying scripts might not be bad, but ideally you don&amp;rsquo;t want to manually deploy anything, so I wrote a little script that allow me to install the SQL scripts in my toolbox to any environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating a 40TB SQL Server Database</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/migrating-40tb-sql-server-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/migrating-40tb-sql-server-database/</guid>
      <description>Initially, I wasn’t sure whether to write about this migration project, but when I randomly asked if people would be interested, the response was overwhelming. This was a long, kind of boring, very repetitive, and at times incredibly frustrating project, but I learned a lot, and maybe someone else will learn from this too. There may be far better ways to move this amount of data. In the path I went down, there was a huge amount of juggling that had to take place (I’ll explain that later).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using powershell to fix server space issues</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/using-powershell-to-fix-server-space-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 18:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/using-powershell-to-fix-server-space-issues/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, we were running into severe disk space and memory issues on our development servers at work. Our set-up is a bit odd, we have 3 servers - one for the transactions, one for the web interface, and the final one for reporting. Using transactional replication we have databases that can exist on all 3 servers. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s can be a real nightmare to maintain, but anyone who works with replication already knows this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Saturday Adventures</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/sql-saturday-adventures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 16:50:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/sql-saturday-adventures/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks bit over a month ago, I took the plunge and attended my very first SQL Saturday, SQL Saturday #370 in Phoenix. I&amp;rsquo;ve never had a chance to go to any of the local user group events or another SQL Saturday due to scheduling issues, etc. but this year I reshuffled things so I could take part. I&amp;rsquo;m really glad that I did, I truly learned a lot of stuff and I also realized I know more than I probably give myself credit for.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
