<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Availibility Group on Taryn Pratt</title>
    <link>https://tarynpivots.com/tags/availibility-group/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Availibility Group on Taryn Pratt</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 06:00:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://tarynpivots.com/tags/availibility-group/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How Stack Overflow upgraded from Windows Server 2012</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-stack-overflow-upgraded-from-windows-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-stack-overflow-upgraded-from-windows-2012/</guid>
      <description>Warning: This post is long. While working through this massive server upgrade/migration process, tears were shed, many cuss words were said, along with a general feeling of frustration, which ultimately culminated into extreme happiness once the migration was completed. The scale and complexity of the implementation factor into the length of this post, and I’ll share my thought process on how this was executed, so here goes.
Last year, when we upgraded to SQL Server 2017 we didn&amp;rsquo;t make any changes to the operating system on our main production servers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How we upgraded Stack Overflow to SQL Server 2017</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-we-upgraded-stackoverflow-to-sql-server-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 19:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/how-we-upgraded-stackoverflow-to-sql-server-2017/</guid>
      <description>This post has been rattling around in my head for months, and with SQL Server 2019 on the horizon, I figured I&amp;rsquo;d finally put my thoughts down, especially since I know we might hit some of the same issues when we upgrade.
A quick background, when I became the DBA at Stack Overflow, we had various versions of SQL Server in place &amp;mdash; the majority were at some level of SQL Server 2016, each with a different CU or SP installed.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>