<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Career on Taryn Pratt - Pivots and other SQL fun</title>
    <link>https://tarynpivots.com/tags/career/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Career on Taryn Pratt - Pivots and other SQL fun</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 06:00:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://tarynpivots.com/tags/career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>T-SQL Tuesday #122 - Impostor Syndrome</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/t-sql-tuesday-122-impostor-syndrome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 06:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/t-sql-tuesday-122-impostor-syndrome/</guid>
      <description>This month&amp;rsquo;s T-SQL Tuesday is hosted by Jon Shaulis, who has asked that we talk about impostor syndrome. This subject is close to my heart, as I have dealt with it throughout my career.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t study computer science or engineering in college. I never even took a computer class. I sort of just fell into working as a web developer because I had someone tell me they wouldn’t hire me due to lack of experience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally, My first PASS Summit</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/my-first-pass-summit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/my-first-pass-summit/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with SQL Server for a long time, and have always wanted to attend PASS. For one reason of another, with numerous employers, I hadn’t been able to go. The answer was always no. &amp;lt;insert sad face&amp;gt;
The biggest blocker was always the cost.
The conference is expensive.
Seattle is expensive.
It has always been impossible to get my employer to foot the bill for it.
This year I was incredibly lucky that my employer, Stack Overflow, paid for my trip to PASS Summit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pivoting yet again - New blog and domain</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/pivoting-yet-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/pivoting-yet-again/</guid>
      <description>Almost a year ago, in November 2017, I moved back into a more technical role at Stack Overflow and became a Database Administrator. During this time, I have wanted to relaunch my blog, as it&amp;rsquo;s been over three years since I really wrote anything (yes, I&amp;rsquo;m terrible).
Well, that time has finally come.
After spending a few weeks, looking at various options to replace Wordpress, I finally decided on using Hugo and Netlify.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ch Ch Ch Changes are afoot</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/ch-ch-ch-changes-are-afoot/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2015 22:49:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/ch-ch-ch-changes-are-afoot/</guid>
      <description>Well it&amp;rsquo;s been an interesting couple months and there are quite a few changes going on in my life, but before I get into what&amp;rsquo;s coming up, I feel that I need to give a bit of an overview of my journey thus far.
I never thought about becoming a developer. When I was growing up, I loved school (yeah, I&amp;rsquo;m weird), I loved math and science (even weirder), I was going to be a doctor, work on genetics, or something similar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Late to the party</title>
      <link>https://tarynpivots.com/post/late-to-the-party/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 02:00:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tarynpivots.com/post/late-to-the-party/</guid>
      <description>Boy, I am sure behind the times with having a tech type of blog, but being late is better than never. I am going to try to use this platform to discuss some of my tech journeys while I delve into my new job as a DBA developer. I have worked on SQL Server in the past, but I will be venturing into Oracle development as well as more in depth SQL Server stuff.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>